And let's see, let's go for it.
And let's see, we have an alteration.
Okay, now next we're going to
introduce some
validation constraints on the data.
For example, for example, in clients I
can come and insert and I can, for
example, in identifier
say name, José Vicente, last name
Carratalá Sánchez,
telephone, a telephone number, of course,
but I'm going to put, I'm going to put, I'm going to
put 52
and email, well email@info.
Continuous.  He let me, he let me
insert it, but I know this isn't
right, okay?  I know that at some
point we're going to examine
phone 52, what we were talking about
before, right?  At least here in Spain, you
couldn't have the phone number 52.
Instead, I insist,
assuming the Spanish case, it would have to have a
minimum of nine characters.  It's more like a
minimum of nine characters, unless
they're special numbers like
1004 and all that, but let's assume there
aren't any special numbers.   The
same thing happens with email, right?  And
we've entered information, but it's not
valid; it doesn't have the structure of an
email.  Data validations
can be done, we'll see, obviously on
the programming side,
but they can also be done on the
database side.  So for
example, I'm going to come over here and say eh,
now alter table to add validation
and
phone
must be equal to nine characters.
Let's see.  And here,
okay?  So let's add a
constraint,
okay?  Let's add a constraint
phone constraint point sql
and activate it.  So now I
come here, I go to SQL, I grab the
code, I paste it, I run it.  Uh, it says
error, but okay, fine, no problem.
Let's see.  Is Ah, of course, of course, of course.
What's going on?  What's going on?  Well, as
soon as there is a record
that doesn't comply, then it no longer complies, right?
So I'm going to delete this record,
I'm going to enter that SQL,
we're going to continue and it tells us okay,
okay?  The one that was there no longer
complied.  So I go to clients, I'm
going to insert myself, I say, "José
Vicente, last name Garratalá, wait,
where am I hearing that?"
here.  Okay.  Okay.  Come on.
Okay.
And now next.  And now
phone 52 or 53, email
info or onfo.  I hit continue and it
says, "No, you can't insert that
record because you don't meet the
condition."  Okay, so I come over
here and say, "Okay, okay, okay, okay,
okay. So I'm going to fulfill the condition.
620 89 16 18."  Okay, so I hit
continue and it's inserted
successfully.  But the email is not
valid, the email is onfo.  Onfo cannot
be an email.  An email has to be
something@something.
Extension or something or person@domain.
So now next I say now
another one
for email.
Okay, we also use check
and okay, the check is going to be very
limited.
Look, let's get in.  Oh my goodness, this
is a regular expression,
okay?  Uh, well, I don't want to get
too involved right now.  002 email.Ssql SQL with
regular expressions, but let's get to
it.  Okay, now I execute,
I'll explain the regular expression later
, it's quite a long story,
okay?  So,
well, I'm trying to put in a
validation, but it's going to give an error because it's
going to tell me that the one that's there no longer
exists, okay?  Okay.  The current one no longer
complies, so clients, so
delete, so okay, so SQL.
So I alter the table, okay?  Now
yes.  And if I try to enter a record
and say, "Jose Vicente
Carratalá, phone 620 89 16 18, that's
enough, but email info isn't."  I click
continue and it says check email format is
violated.  Okay, but if I tell him
info@jocarsa.com,
I tell him to continue and then he does
comply.  So, as we can see,
validation restrictions help me
ensure that the data is entered correctly,
meaning that I can't accept any
type of data, but rather I can
control the data that actually travels to
the database.  All right, let's let's let's let's let's let's
continue.  Let's
continue with indexes.
Indexes allow us to establish, in
fact, before, when I created a
key, what we see here is an index, it
allows us to index the information.
Also, eventually, what we can
do is specify what we want, for
example, to add one more field, which is the
DNI, the DNI, the NIF, the NIE or
whatever, okay?  Or even if it's the carré from the
video store, I don't care, okay?  But a
key, the indexes, therefore,
allow us to better manage the
information.  I'm not going to do the
index exercise now; we'll leave that for
later because I need
data in the database, but we'll
work on that later.  Okay, and then
and then we have the null value next
.  The null value allows us to
specify what happens when I
don't save data.  For example, I'm going to
insert and I say, "The name is Juan. I
don't put the last name and I put the phone number
and the email.
I hit insert,
I hit continue and I was able to
insert it. And as we can see,
an empty column is inserted. So instead of
inserting an empty column, what I can
do is tell it that there are certain fields
that can be null, can be not.
I mean,
ah, let's see. Make surnames
null. Insert null.
Let's see. Exercises. Alter 001.
surname nul punql.
So surname nul SQL.
Let's see. We alter the column. Let's
alter the column.
Okay. And now, what happens when
we insert a
client? You see? Right now, nothing. I'm going
to insert
and I go to José Vicente. I go to nothing.
Okay, you see there that okay, that it puts it
as null, it's automatically null.
Phone 620 89 1718. Email
info@jocarsa.com.
Okay, so I'm
going to continue and we'll notice that
now it hasn't inserted an empty string,
but now what it has done is
insert the value null.
And you'll say, "Hey, what's the
difference between null and empty string?"
Because in the end, they're the same thing; they're
basically just an empty space. Well,
no, not really. This
might not be of
capital importance right now, but later on, you'll see that
it is. There's a meme, the null
toilet paper roll meme,
that tells us that one thing
is zero
and another thing is null. Okay, zero means there could
be a value but there is no value. There could
be a paper but there is no paper. And null
means there is no value. The value
is zero and there is no value are not the same. Okay, just
remember this toilet paper roll meme
and we'll come back to it later.
And now, I'm going to take a
little jump. I'm going to skip over
these parts for now, the
data description language.
We've seen it before, really, the
data control language, and we're going to start
creating queries.
To create queries, what I'm going to
do in this case is insert
a series of sample data. We'll
talk about insertion later, but
we're going to insert 001
sample data
into the database using SQL.
We'll talk about foreign keys and
views and all that later, but not right now.
Okay, let's go to the sample data.
Uh, create
sample data for
clientes table 20 customers,
20 Spanish customers
so that the first and last names are
in Spanish and all that.
Perfect.
Well, I'm going to execute,
I'm going to execute this query. I
copy the code,
paste it, and I'm going to execute this
query simply so that in
clientes, I don't have, I'm going to empty the
table, I don't have, uh, an empty table, but
rather I have a
respectable set of data. I'm going to continue,
and we'll see how now in clientes, there
are 20 customers, there are 20 rows, and this already looks
different, okay? Here
we can start doing things, okay?
What  Is this the first thing we want to do
when we have data in a table?
Well, the first thing we want to
do is project, select, and
sort. Okay, let's start by
performing the simplest of
operations: 002: selection.
So I come here and tell you, the
simplest of the selections is
select all from clients.
And with this, we begin the most important
of the database operations, which
is select. There are four important ones, but
this is the most important. So if I do
select all from clients,
what happens is that I select everything from
all the clients, but I don't have to
select everything from all the
clients. For example, I
only want to see the names.
So, select
name from clients. I copy,
paste, and check how I only see the
name. I
can't just see the first name. 004. I
select columns. Hey, careful. I
select
columns. I don't just want to see the name.
Let's put it on different lines
so it's a little more organized.
First name, comma, last name.
I can select as many columns as
I want, so I select names and
select  surnames.
In addition, I can perform projections.
Not only can I choose the columns,
but I can also change the
column aliases because name is in
lowercase, which isn't very nice
. Last names aren't very nice. I'm going to
use the AS 005 particle
alias
and I'm going to say name AS name
names of the clients and
last names AS. last names of the clients
with a single quote.
So if I do this,
copy,
paste, select, but as we see,
the
column names are
prettier and more understandable, although
internally, in the database. Hey,
why am I not seeing? Why am I not
seeing the chat? Okay, now although
internally, internally it's still called
name, but visually for the
end user it will be called
client names, which is nicer and more
understandable and ultimately more human.
Okay,
right now, right now, now I'm going to
select everything again. Sort 006.
Let's go back to everything, okay? Select all from
clients.
By default, the records
are  They are ordered based on the identifier, they are
ordered based on how they are
naturally stored in the database, but
let's suppose that I want to store them, I
want to order them by last name. So
next I say 007,
we order by column
and now I come and say select all from
clients,
order by last name
and that's it. Okay. And already wrong, but now we
see it. And here continue and then it
orders them by last name.
Well, I have done something that is not
very good and that is that eh if I do
not put ask or desk in the order buy, that is,
ascending or descending, by default,
My SQL understands that the ordering is
ascending. It's not cool because it's not
good for the computer to understand
things, it's better that we
explain them to it. Therefore, 008 ascending.
It's better that we put Ask,
although technically it's not necessary,
but it's better, it's cleaner. In the
same way, we could also
put descending.
I want them to be ordered from Z to
A.
So I copy,
continue and  They sort from highest to lowest,
from last to first. I ca
n't just sort by a single
criterion, I can sort by multiple. So
010, multiple criteria, and then
I say order by first name ask comma last name
no sorry, sorry, the other way around,
last name ask, first name ask or or desk, whatever you
want.
So I copy, SQL, paste, and sort by
last name. And in the case that there were
two identical last names, then it
would sort alphabetically by
ascending name.
As you can see, yes,
yes, they do go in this order. It's first going to
try to sort these, and if there's a
duplicate in these, then it moves on to
these. And I've given an example with two
columns, and you can put in whatever columns you want
. I mean, if there were, which I
don't think there would be, okay? But if there were the same
last name and first name, then it
sorts by, I don't know, okay? By
ID, by phone, by email,
by whatever you want. It's rare,
but it can happen, obviously.
Let's see, let's see. Just a moment,
I'm going to run a query,  A query
to
make sure I didn't leave anything out before moving on to the next section.
Uh,
let's see.
Uh. Uh. Uh
. Uh. No, I almost left something
important out. Okay.
Oh, no, okay. Okay.
Nothing, perfect. I wanted, wanted, wanted,
wanted, okay, I wanted to check that I didn't
leave something out. Okay, next. Uh,
summary queries, grouping,
compositions, compositions,
subqueries. Okay, well, no, let's look at
a type of query called the we, okay?
That's the conditions within
queries. We can set the following conditions:
011,
uh, clause,
and I'm going to say select from clients
where, and I'm going to say where surnames
equals Castro Vargas.
It equals Castro Vargas. I
execute,
SQL,
I execute, I click
continue, and we see that,
unlike before, I haven't selected
all the records; I've selected
only the record that meets a
specific condition. Now, later
we'll talk about operators,
and we'll talk about boolean operators and
logical operators. In short,
okay?  I say this because I'm going to do a
simple demonstration.
Now, next I say, okay, but
I would like it to find all
the wildcards, starting wildcard,
all those last names like Castro
percentage. The percentage is a wildcard
and it says I want to find all
those users whose last name starts
with Castro and then whatever it is. So
I execute,
I go to SQL, I
execute here
and it tells me Isabel Castro Vargas. Okay, I
can also 013
two wildcards.
So in two wildcards I want to get
all those users who have an astro
in their last name. Two wildcards. It's a
starting wildcard and an ending wildcard.
Or for example Ria from García and all that,
or for example EZ
from Martínez Fernández and all that. So I hit
SQL
continue and it tells me, well look, there
's López, there's Martínez, there's Rodríguez, there's Gómez, there's Fernández, there's López
, there's Hernández, there's... How
curious, uh, Torres, that is, Sánchez, there
's Hernández and there's Domínguez, okay? I
mean, it's  I mean, as you can see,
the we clause allows me to filter,
the we clause allows me to select.
Okay, let's focus on the last
part of today's class. Above all, the
objective of today's class is to verify
that we can now connect to a
database, we can now start making
requests to a database, we
can now start obtaining things from a
database.
Obviously, in the coming weeks, we'll
be connecting programming with the
database, and then we'll connect
programming with markup languages,
and little by little, we'll
interconnect the subjects. Today,
we're in the second week, and we have
n't interconnected anything yet. We're
moving forward in parallel, okay? But
obviously,
what I want you to think about is, wow, how
cool would it be to enter information into a
database and then have Python take that
information from the database and
then display it on a web page.
Okay, so that's what we'll do,
but not yet because we're in the
first week. We're going to talk about
operators. We
're going to talk about operators, and
then projection. Okay,
operators.  Okay. So,
let's talk about
mathematical operators. So, 001
001 arithmetic operators
pun SQL and I say and I say
select
4 + 3 from clients. It's funny. So
, what does this mean?
Well, SQL
select 4 + 3 is 7 7 7 7 7 7 7 7 7 7 7.
What does this mean? Okay, so this
means we can do
mathematical operations with
records. What does mathematical operations mean
? Well, I can do
select 4 + 3,
4 - 3, 4* 3, for example,
and 4/ 3.
Let's run it. We
go on and we have addition and we have
subtraction and we have multiplication and
we have division. And you're going to say,
"But what good does this do?"
Why would I want to multiply things in a
database?  Well, it can be
very useful to us.  So I'm going
to ask GPT Chat next, "
Hello, here, okay?"  And here I'm
going to ask you now I want
sample data for the product table.
20 products.   Let's
go there.
No, but I already have the board.   I
already have the board.   I
already have the board.  Databases.
Data model.  Terminology.
Create product table.
Okay, I don't want you to create a new table for me
,
what I want is for you to create 20
products for the table I already had.
Let's see it.
Okay, as you can see, from what I
was telling you before, from what I was
telling you on the first day, it's good to
use artificial intelligence, it's
good to use GPT chat to help you,
but of course, you have to know how to program
because you have to know how to read that you
have said, "I want, I want products"
and the GPT chat almost got me into trouble.  He
says to me, "Okay, so let's create a
table."
So you as a human being have to
remember and say, "No, no, I already
had a board, don't believe me, it's another
board."  Okay, so it's not like you just ask
Chat GPT for something and it does everything for you, right?
You have to know how to program and you have to
know what you're doing to know
when you're doing it right, but
when you have to say, "No, no, no,
I already have it, give me this board."  Okay,
fine.  We copy code.  Let's load up,
shall we?  Let's load 002
sample
SQL data.
Let's run it against the
database.
Therefore, we load 20 sample products
and with the 20 sample products we are going
to demonstrate what
arithmetic operations are useful for,
because they are useful.  So,
I'm going to say the following next.  003,
VAT calculation.  I know that the general VAT in
Spain is 21%.
So I would like the
price representing the tax base in this table to
also represent the
VAT tax, okay?  You might say, "But
this wouldn't be calculated in the
programming."
The answer is, well, yes, it can be
calculated in programming, but it
can also be calculated in the
database.  It's a matter of
the developer deciding whether to
calculate it in one part or
another.  So select from
select to disk from eh products.
Okay.  And no and no select disc.  I don't
want to.  Let's select columns
I want the name.
I want the, well, the, look, the
description doesn't matter to me right now.
I want the price and now next
I want the price multiplied by 0.21,
that is, I'm using, as you can
see, a multiplication eh operator
, an arithmetic
multiplication operator.
Copy, copy, execute.
And when selecting, we
can check that it gives me the price
of the product, what we would call the
taxable base and the VAT.  Of course, the thing
is that the price of 0.21 doesn't look very
nice, right?  So column alias,
column alias and I say price as
taxable base.
which is more beautiful, more human, more
understandable.
This AS was 21%
and this is the
name of the product.
So I copy.
So,
sorry, not here.  So I run it
and we'll see how in this case it doesn't matter to me
, but the column names
are prettier and more understandable and
more human and more workable in an
application.
Now, as you can imagine,
what I want is to get the total as well
.   I
add the total and to add the total I'm going
to say that let's see, I want this and
I want price plus, well, really yes,
we're going to make it eh complex, okay?
Price plus price by 0.21.   I
know you might say,
"Well, this is the same as putting the price
multiplied by 1.21, yes, but
this way we practice both the
addition operator and the multiplication operator,
okay?" It's an excuse, so just do total
invoice
or total price, let's say, because there is
n't an invoice yet. So I copy,
SQL, paste, continue and here we have it.
We have the tax base, we have the
21% VAT and we have the total price.
So just like in
programming languages,
in databases there are also
operators and they have a very
specific use, as you'll see, in the same way as they
do in databases. Let's see, wait
a minute. It won't be open now.
Hello. Hello. Are
you coming for that?
Okay. Hm. You can't. Look, I'll tell you.
I'm finishing databases with the
first years. I'll stay in fifteen minutes and
then fifteen minutes until the
second years. You can come on the 45th. Perfect. And
so from 45 o'clock on the dot we'll finish  That.
Yes. Alarm. Alarm. Very well. Very well.
Sure, sure.
Okay, now that's it. And now
to be able to enter later. That's it. That's it.
Okay, that's it,
okay? So, next we're going to see
more operators, such as,
for example, the
comparison operators, okay? Which
I probably think will be the last ones we'll
see today, okay? Uh, 006
comparison operators.
And then I say
select 4 is less than or greater than three. We
saw the comparison operators
the other day in
programming languages ​​in Python,
okay? So I copy,
SQL, paste, continue. Okay, is it true
that four is greater than 3? It tells me one,
is it true? Or 007,
false comparison.
Or is it true that 4 is less than 3.
So, uh, it will tell me false. It will
tell me false, it will tell me zero. Once again,
you'll say, "Well, what does this
mean, that I put
one or zero?"
Well, what does it mean in  In this case,
I can perform
conditional validations within MySQL. For
example, I go to the products table
and I'm going to say that those products,
for example, that have a price greater
than €1,000 or €500, I don't care what
you say, if someone
buys something from me for more than €500, I'll give them
the shipping costs. Okay, there's no
shipping costs, but if someone
buys something for less than €500, then they
do have shipping costs, okay? So,
what I'm going to do next is the
following.
Let's see. 008,
eh, condition,
and I say select name, comma, price, comma,
price is less than 500.
Let's see it.
We execute.
We go to SQL,
we execute,
and it tells us that some are zero, some are
one, and some are whatever. Okay?
Prices. I'm going to put alias
column alias.
And this is ash, I do
n't know, you know? Shipping or something like that
or shipping costs
or let's see. Hm. Shipping charge.
Okay, so how much will the
Transport. Well, I don't know, it could be a
fixed value, it could be a variable value, I don't know.
Okay, let's see,
and hm, let's execute
SQL,
okay? Continue, and okay, load
transport. Okay. And now, and now I
want to say
price,
this
and this multiplied, let's see if it lets me.
Multiplied by 200. I'm going to tell you that
the transport price is going to be 200,
okay? Why? Because I don't know.
Transport price.
So I copy,
paste,
execute. No, it's not valid. Okay.
Okay. Ah, I imagined because this is
a true false. Okay. Okay. I'm going to
tell it ifels. I'm going to
tell it ifels. Okay, I see you're
trying. It doesn't exist. It's okay. It's an
if, yes.
Okay, no, we're not going to use an if, and
later I'll explain the case, and so
we make it as simple as possible, okay?
If the price is less than 500, load
transport. And now if the price is less than
500, load  200. If not, I charge zero.
So now,
sorry, now I come here, I
execute SQL and now yes. Okay, if it weighs,
if it weighs, if it's worth more than 500, no, I don't
charge shipping. But if it's worth less than
500, I charge shipping, so in the
end,
010 total with shipping.
Okay, a moment
and okay, okay, okay. Okay. And total,
okay. And this is the total, total order.
The VAT would be missing, obviously it
's 200 plus price.
I take,
execute,
execute. Mm. Okay, Martín. Hm. Ah,
sorry. 200 plus price goes here
and no. Okay. Error. Ah, how strange.
A comma. I'm missing a comma before it. Total
order.
No.
Ah, yeah. Damn, I'm missing a comma. Geez.
It's possible. I'm missing a comma.
Okay. And continue. And there we have the
total order with shipping. Okay,
something's wrong there. Something's wrong there because Ah,
yeah, no,  200 plus the price. Ah,
sorry, sorry.
Okay, if not,
of course, no, this isn't zero, but it's the
price.
Okay,
the false case
is the false case is the price.
Now, okay. If it's less than that, it doesn't include
shipping and it's worth what it's worth, but if it
's less than that, you have to charge €200 for
shipping. I'm telling you €200 because I just
made that up.
Moral. Moral. And with this, we'll
end today's class because
I have a small meeting in the last
15 minutes.
The moral. The moral, basically,
to understand each other, is that with what we've
seen so far, we have access to
MySQL. We can load data, and once we
load data into a database
like MySQL, we can start
making a lot of requests, okay?
We can request requests, we can request
products, we can request customers, we
can sort, we can filter,
we can do whatever we want with
customers. The concept of MySQL
is complex at first because it's like
MySQL forces you to save things in
a very specific way, and it's true that's the
case, but if  If we respect that
methodology, if we respect those rules,
then we'll be able to enjoy
the SQL language, which,
as you can see, is a very simple and
accessible language. And the commands,
that's exactly it. Okay? The
commands are designed so that you
say you want to select something and you
want to sort it in a specific way.
The database will then
handle all the magic inside.
Okay? Indeed, the
SQL commands are to offer you, the
human being, an interface that I think is
reasonably easy to use.
I always say, if you speak English, you already
know half of SQL, because
the SQL language is to select I don't know what, I do
n't know how many from the product table. I
mean, it's practically English.
The SQL language is the simplest
you can find, even simpler than
Python, which is to say, next
time we'll continue on Monday. And
so, uh, do what I told you at the
end of the afternoon today, which is to
do the exercises. Do
everything that I  I'll have you
repeat it and get ready because
next week we'll start doing
activities, we'll start doing
subunits and units little by little.
Obviously, I'm not going to cram a
ton of exercises into you on the first day and
nothing, and we'll start the assessments.
If necessary, on Monday we'll do more
mock exams for the rest of the subjects so you can be
sure of how
the activities are going, and that's it.
Okay, so that's it, see you on Monday
for the next classes. Take advantage of
the weekend to review and
practice and to follow the rule that
everything I do, you do too, and that's
it. Okay? Come on, guys, see you
later.